Guide to the WSU Physical Education Department Records 1921-1962
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
WSU Physical Education Department Records
1921-1962
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 370
1.5 linear feet of shelf space 2 boxes
Planning documents, budgets, and roll books from Washington State University’s Physical Education program. Of note are documents relating to civil defense uses of the Smith Gym in the 1960s, including publications and documents from Whitman County and from the Department of Defense.
Men’s physical education at WSU dates to the campus’s first days, while women's physical education began at WSU in 1901. In 1964 the departments of Physical Education for Women (housed in the Helen Smith Gymnasium) and Physical Education for Men were created out of the College of Education. The two departments merged in 1985.
The collection consists of documents collected by or created by the Washington State University Department of Physical Education for Women. Included are a volume of departmental accounts (1921-1940) and roll books from 1921-1922, but the majority of the collection dates from the 1960s and deals with planning for the uses of Smith Gym in the event of a nuclear attack.
Due to its large size the accounting book, covering 1929-1940, is placed first in the collection in its own box. Materials after that are arranged in chronological order.
This collection is open and available for research use.
These records were transferred to Washington State University Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections in December, 1992 by Barbara Hagedorn of the College of Education, and retained as UA1992-39.
WSU Libraries’ MASC also holds Physical Education Records covering 1908-1967 (Archives 145) and 1947-1983 (Archives 377), as well as two sets of Women's Physical Education Department Records: 1923-1976 (Archives 19), and 1973-1981 (Archives 300).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Department of Physical Education and Athletics; State College of Washington. Women's Physical Education Department.
Physical Education for women--Washington (State)--Pullman--Archives
Colleges and Universities.
- Accounting book, Women’s Physical Education, 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Class Roll book, 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- “_The_ Field House Memo,” April 13, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- W.A.C. Field Manual, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- A Model Passive Defense Plan with Particular Reference for Passive Defensive Measures Against Radioactive Fallout. 6158 USAR, R&D Unit, Pullman, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Fallout Protection – What to Know and Do About Nuclear Attack, Department of Defense / Office of Civil Defense, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Psychological and Social Adjustment in a Simulated Shelter. DoD/OCD, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Guide for Community Fallout Shelter Management. DoD/OCD, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Federal Guidance for State and Local Civil Defense – National Fallout Shelter Survey and Marking Program. DoD/OCD, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Civil Defense documents – Map of Washington State University Designated Shelter Areas; Shelter Registration card, Whitman county, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Shelter Management Course. Washington State Department of Civil Defense, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Civil Defense documents – management of Smith Gym, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Donor correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)